现在想想不同的方法是有用的
Now it's useful to think about different ways
我们可以对类型和不同类型的操作进行分类
that we can classify types and different kinds of operations
对那些类型。
on those types.
我们已经遇到了一些。
And we've already encountered some of them.
类型可以是可变的或不可变的。
Types can be either mutable or immutable.
这是一个非常重要的特征，
And this is a very important feature of a type,
是否该类型的对象--
whether the object of that type--
该类型的值创建后是否可以更改。
whether a value of that type can be changed once it's created.
它是否提供在执行时，
Does it provide operations that, when executed,
导致其他操作的结果
cause the results of other operations
对同一个对象给出不同的结果？
on the same object to give different results?
这就是我们所说的可变抽象数据类型。
That's actually what we mean by a mutable abstract data type.
所以在Java中，日期类型是可变的，
So in Java, the date type is mutable,
因为你有固定的月份
because you have operations like set month
你可以观察到这个月的变化
that make a change that you can then observe with the get month
操作。
operation.
但是字符串是不可变的，因为它是
But string is immutable, because it's
操作，那些改变字符串的操作，
operations, the ones that seem to change a string,
实际创建一个新的字符串对象
actually create a new string objects
保持现有价值不变，
and leave the existing value unchanged,
据你所知。
as far as you can tell.
有时一个类型以两种形式出现--可变和不可变
Sometimes a type appears in two forms-- a mutable and immutable
形式。
form.
例如，字符串生成器是字符串的可变版本，
So string builder, for example, is a mutable version of string,
虽然这两种Java类型肯定不同，
although the two are certainly not the same Java type,
而且在Java中它们是不可互换的。
and they're not interchangeable in Java.
因此可变和不可变是类型的重要属性。
So mutable and immutable are important properties of a type.
类型的操作也可以分类。
The operations of a type can also be classified.
创建者是创建类型的新对象的操作。
A creator is an operation that creates new objects of a type.
它可能将其他类型的对象作为参数。
It might take an object of some other type as an argument.
生产者从旧对象创建新对象
A producer creates new objects from old objects
相同类型的。
of the same type.
例如，对于字符串，concat方法是一个生产者。
So for string, for example, the concat method is a producer.
它需要你从两条线开始，
It needs you to start with two strings,
它产生了一个新的。
and it produces a new one.
观察者获取类型为的对象并返回属性
Observers take an object of the type and return properties
属于那种类型的——属于那种对象
of that type-- of that object, which
必须是另一种类型。
have to be a different type.
例如，list的size方法返回一个int。
So the size method of list, for example, returns an int.
所以size是list的观察者。
So size is an observer for list.
最后，一个变异操作
And then, finally, a mutator operation actually
更改对象值。
changes an object values.
所以add方法列表对一个列表进行了变异
So the add method list mutates a list
通过在末尾添加元素。
by adding an element to the end.
现在，我们可以总结这些区别
Now, we can summarize these distinctions
基本上使用函数符号。
schematically using basically functional notation.
阅读这篇文章的方式是大写的，这是我们抽象的类型。
And the way to read this is capital T is our abstract type.
例如，它可能是字符串。
So it might be string, for example.
所以一根弦的创造者
And so a creator for a string is going
获取某些其他类型的0个或多个值--
to take 0 or more values of some other types--
所以小写的t代表任何其他类型
so lowercase t just represents any other type
除了我们所说的抽象类型--
other than the abstract type we're talking about--
在常规正则表达式中，星号表示0或更多
and the star means 0 or more in conventional regular expression
符号。
notation.
其他类型的还要0个
It'll take 0 more of some other type
并生成抽象类型的值。
and produce a value of the abstract type.
生产者至少有一个价值--
A producer takes at least one value--
这就是加号的意思--至少是一个或多个
that's what the plus means-- it means one or more-- at least
抽象类型的一个值，一些0
one value of the abstract type, some 0
或者其他类型的值，
or more values of some other types,
并生成抽象类型的值。
and produces a value of the abstract type.
观察者从一个或多个值开始
An observer starts with one of more values
抽象类型的，其他类型的0或更多，
of the abstract type, 0 or more of some other type,
并产生另一种类型。
and produces another type.
它不产生抽象类型。
It does not produce the abstract type.
然后，最后，一个变异器接受一个或多个值
And then, finally, a mutator takes one or more value
抽象类型，可能还有其他一些值，
of the abstract type, possibly some other values,
通常，在Java中返回void。
and, normally, returns void in Java.
因为你只是
That is returns nothing because you only
执行它的效果。
execute it for its effect.
但有时可能返回类型本身的值
But some times may return values of the type itself
或其他类型的值。
or values of some other type.
现在在Java中执行creator操作，并且
Now creator operation in Java, and
任何其他面向对象的编程语言
any other object-oriented programming languages
像Python和JavaScript一样
like Python and JavaScript, is often
实现为使用new调用的构造函数。
implemented as a constructor that you called using new.
但这不一定。
But it doesn't have to be.
创建者可以只是一个静态方法
A creator can simply be a static method
相反，就像一张加薪清单。
instead, like a raise as list.
实现的Creator通常是静态方法
Creator-implemented are static methods often
调用工厂方法。
called a factory methods.
这是一个实现创建者的设计模式。
This is a design pattern for implementing creators.
实现的其他创建者示例
Other examples of creators implemented
as factory方法在字符串中包含方法的值。
as factory methods include the value of methods in the string.
重要的是这些是静态的，
And it's important that these are static,
因为如果它们不是静止的，你
because if they were not static, you
必须有一个字符串的现有值
would have to have an existing value of string
打电话给他们。
to call them on.
然后他们就不再是创造者了，
And then they wouldn't be a creator,
他们实际上是个制片人。
they would actually be a producer.
变异器通常由void返回类型发出信号。
Mutators are often signaled by a void return type.
返回void的方法必须是
A method that returns void must be
需要某种副作用，
called for some kind of side effect,
因为它不返回任何东西。
because it doesn't otherwise return anything.
但并不是所有的突变子都返回空域。
But not all mutators return void.
例如，set.add返回一个布尔值
For example, set.add returns a Boolean
它告诉你这套衣服是否真的换了。
that tells you whether the set was actually changed.
在Java的图形用户界面中
In Java's graphical user interface to a kit
component.add返回对象本身，
component.add returns the object itself,
这很有用，因为这样你可以添加另一个
which is useful because that way you can just add another .add
叫到最后，把他们绑在一起。
call to the end, and chain them together.
下面是一些抽象数据的例子
Here are some examples of abstract data
类型，以及按种类分组的某些操作。
types, along with some of their operations grouped by kind.
所以让我们想想，例如，
So let's think about, for example,
Java的原始整数类型int。
Java's primitive integer type, int.
Int是不可变的，所以它不应该
Int is immutable, so it shouldn't
做任何变异操作。
have any mutator operations.
它的创造者是什么？
What are its creators?
好吧，Java有数字文本，0、1、2等等。
Well, Java has numeric literals, 0, 1, 2, and so forth.
它们是有效的创造者
These are effectively creators that produce-- that
生成int类型的值。
generate a value of int type.
生产商是什么？
What are the producers?
如果你从整数开始，
Well, if you're starting with integers,
你可以把两个整数加上
you can combine two integers with plus
得到另一个整数。
to get another integer.
同样，用减号，乘以，除以。
Likewise, with minus and times and divides.
观察员呢？
What about the observers?
好吧，你可以取两个整数，然后比较它们。
Well, you can take two integers, and you can compare them.
这给了你一个布尔值。
And that gives you a Boolean back.
所以这是一个观察者。
So that's an observer.
当然，它没有变异因子
And, of course, it has no mutators
因为它是不可变的。
because it's immutable.
另一个例子是list，Java的list类型。
Another example is list, Java's list type.
列表是不可变的。
List is immutable.
List碰巧是一个接口，这意味着它本身
List happens to be an interface, which means that by itself it
没有实现，但其他类提供
doesn't have an implementation, but that other classes provide
实际执行。
the actual implementation.
我们以前也看过。
And we've looked at that before.
数组列表和链接列表是示例
Array list and linked list are examples
可用于实现列表接口的类的。
of classes that you can use that implement the list interface.
但是列表接口本身是一种类型。
But the list interface itself is a type.
我们可以把它看作一种类型，
And we can think about it as a type,
我们可以谈谈它提供的操作。
and we can talk about the operations that it provides.
这些是接口的方法。
Those are the methods of the interface.
那么它的创造者是什么呢？
So what are its creators?
好吧，列表本身实际上没有任何创建者。
Well, list by itself actually does not have any creators.
Java中有一个限制
There's a limitation in Java that you're not
允许将构造函数放入接口中。
allowed to put constructors into an interface.
所以您必须使用这些类中的一个构造函数
So you have to use a constructor from one of these classes that
提供列表接口，如数组列表或链接
provides the list interface, like your array list or linked
列出构造函数。
list constructors.
还有像collection singleton list这样的工厂方法，
There's also factory methods like collection singleton list,
它是一个静态方法
which is a static method that will
生成包含任意
produce a list containing a single object of an arbitrary
键入。
type.
有哪些制片人？
What producers are there?
好吧，例如，我们看了不可修改的列表，
Well, for example, we've looked at the unmodifiable list,
rapper是一个静态方法，它接受一个列表
rapper which is a static method that takes a list
并生成另一个列表。
and produces another list.
另一份名单的重要特征
And the important feature of that other list
这是不可改变的，你不被允许
is that it's immutable, that you aren't allowed
称之为变异因子。
to call any of it's mutators.
名单上有哪些观察员？
What observers does list have?
好吧，有些尺寸是
Well, some of them are size which
以整数形式返回列表的大小，
returns the size of the list as an integer,
获取返回列表中特定元素的。
get which returns a particular element from the list.
还有其他的。
And there are others as well.
如果我们查看列表，就会发现其他API。
If we looked at lists, API would be find others.
因为列表是可变的，所以它也
And because list is mutable, it also
有变异，比如加，除，等等。
has mutators, like add, and remove, and at all.
这里有一个作为静态方法实现的mutator。
Here is a mutator that is implemented as a static method.
最后，字符串——Java字符串类型——字符串是不可变的。
Finally, strings-- Java string types-- string is immutable.
它有什么创造者？
What creators does it have?
好吧，它有很多你可以使用的构造器。
Well, it has a number of constructors that you can use.
它有哪些生产商？
What producers does it have?
可以连接两个字符串。
You can concatenate two strings.
可以获取字符串的子字符串
You can take the substring of a string which
生成另一个字符串。
produces another string.
可以将字符串转换为大小写。
You can convert strings to uppercase and lowercase.
它有哪些观察员？
What observers does it have?
Length将给您一个字符串的整数长度。
Length will give you the length of a string as an integer.
随便给你个角色
Char at will give you the character
在字符串中的特定位置。
at a particular position in the string.
它有突变子吗。
Does it have any mutators.
不，它是不变的。
No, it's immutable.
所以这一分类的创造者，生产者，观察者
So this classification of creators, producers, observers
变异的，可变的，不变的，
and mutators and mutable and immutable,
它给了我们一些有用的术语
it gives us some useful terminology
用于思考操作和类型。
for thinking about operations and types.
这不完美。
It's not perfect.
在复杂的数据类型中，可能有
In complicated data types, there may
是一些既生产又变异的操作，
be some operations that are both a producer and a mutator,
例如。
for example.
有些人把生产者这个词保留下来
Some people reserve the term producer
只适用于没有变异的手术。
only for operations that do no mutation.